Guide to the Campaign for a Hate Free Oregon records 1989-1993
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Campaign for a Hate Free Oregon records
1989-1993
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 2988-3
Campaign for a Hate Free Oregon
3.6 cubic feet 8 document cases
Records of an Oregon political organization that opposed anti-lesbian/gay ballot initiatives in the early 1990s. Includes correspondence, contribution lists, records and receipts of expenditures, bank statements, volunteer and employee logs, election reports to the Oregon Secretary of State, and organizing and strategy materials. The organization was also known as the Right To Privacy PAC and the "No On 9" campaign of 1992-1993.
Historical Note
Ballot Measure 9 on the 1992 general election ballot in Oregon was an attempt by the Oregon Citizens Alliance (OCA) to amend the Oregon constitution to prohibit the enactment of laws by the state, counties, or cities that outlaw discrimination against homosexual or bisexual persons, and to require public schools in Oregon to teach students that homosexuality was "wrong," "unnatural," "perverse," and "abnormal." The Campaign for a Hate Free Oregon (CHFO) was the organization formed to defeat Measure 9.
On November 3, 1992, after a vigorous campaign attracting national attention, Measure 9 lost 56.5% - 43.5% -- although the measure carried 21 of Oregon's 36 counties. The same day, Colorado voted on a measure (Amendment 2) containing a similar prohibition against the enactment of civil rights laws for homosexual and bisexual persons. The Colorado measure passed 53% - 47% but was ultimately found unconstitutional by the United States Supreme Court on May 20, 1996 in the case Romer v. Evans et al. These were the first such statewide ballot measures in the United States. Later efforts in Idaho in 1994 and Maine in 1995, and another attempt in Oregon in 1994 (Measure 13), all were defeated by voters.
Items include a small amount of correspondence, contributions lists, expenditures, bank statements, volunteer and employee logs, election reports to the Oregon Secretary of State, organizing and strategy material, and other materials relating to the "No on 9" campaign of 1992.
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series A: No on 9 campaign materials
Series B: Other related materials
The collection is open to the public.
The materials were collected by Fred Neal, who served as Treasurer of the organization. They were donated to the Oregon Historical Society via the Gay and Lesbian Archives of the Pacific Northwest (GLAPN).
Acquired from Fred Neal, July 1996, Library Accession 22762.
Additional records of the Right to Privacy PAC are designated Coll 281 in the Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Neal, Fred--Archives
Campaign for a Hate Free Oregon--Archives; Right to Privacy (organization)--Archives; Oregon Citizens Alliance
Oregon--Politics and government--1951-
Gays--Oregon; Gays--Legal status, laws, etc.--Oregon; Gay liberation--Oregon; Homophobia--Oregon; Elections--Oregon; Lesbians--Oregon; Referendum--Oregon
Oregon; Gays and Lesbians; Political Campaigns
Financial reports; Letters (correspondence); Minutes
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Right to Privacy PAC - Campaign For A Hate Free Oregon: No On 9 Campaign Materials, 1989-1993; Series A
  - Right To Privacy PAC Financial Statements, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Right To Privacy PAC Bylaws, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Right To Privacy PAC Sexual Orientation Discrimination, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/3)
    Draft legislation and notes concerning strategy for obtaining a statewide law banning sexual orientation discrimination.
  - Right To Privacy PAC Board Minutes & Reports, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Right To Privacy PAC Board Members & Executive Director Position Descriptions, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Right To Privacy PAC Miscellaneous Materials, circa 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Miscellaneous Organization Materials, circa 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/7)
    Not all NW region; Oregon organizations include ACLU Oregon chapter; Central Oregon Coalition for Human Dignity (Bend); Oregon Alliance for Progressive Policy; Veterans for Human Rights (Portland chapter).
  - No On 9 Employee Records, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/8)
    Employee time sheets & lists of salaried employees and consultants working on campaign.
  - Worker's Compensation, circa 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Volunteer Sign-in Sheets, circa 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Sample Stationery from Campaign for a Hate Free Oregon, circa 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/12)
    Includes letters of support, requests for donation receipts, criticism of CHFO, and correspondence regarding a post-election financial dispute between CHFO and an investigator hired by the campaign.
  - Petition to Support a Hate Free Oregon, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/13)
    Signatures gathered from around the country opposing Measure 9.
  - Articles & Editorials re: Measure 9, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/14)
    From Oregon newspapers opposing Measure 9.
  - Why Working People Should Vote No on Measure 9, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/15)
    Pamphlet created by Oregon Citizens' Alliance and Coalition for Human Dignity to get union members' support for the No On 9 position.
  - Miscellaneous Resolutions & News Releases, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/16)
    Includes lists of organizations and individuals opposing Measure 9; statements and resolutions of opposition; blank endorsements for public circulation.
  - Statement of Purpose of CHFO, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/17)
    Includes CHFO's description of OCA and the ballot measures.
  - Hollywood Celebrities Pledging Money to Oppose Measure 9, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/18)
    Lists of notable celebrities who pledged money in support of the No On 9 campaign.
  - Opinion Letters from Attorney on Employment Discrimination [Attorney-Client Privileged], 1993 (Box-folder 1/19)
    [Attorney-Client Privileged] Letters contain general infomration on sexual orientation discrimination.
  - Seattle and California Non-Discrimination Laws, undated (Box-folder 1/20)
    Copies of sexual orientation non-discrimination laws enacted in Seattle and statewide in California.
  - Analysis of Passage of Amendment 2 in Colorado and Defeat of Measure 9 in Oregon, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/21)
    Written analyses of why the measures fared differently in two different states.
  - Springfield Charter Amendment, 1992 (Box-folder 1/22)
    Copy of the anti-gay charter amendment adopted by Springfield, Oregon voters (56%-44%) on May 19, 1992. The measure was written by the OCA and placed on the city ballot in anticipation of success with its statewide measure.
  - Vote Abstracts and Polling - Measure 8 (1988) and Measure 9 (1992), 1988, 1992 (Box-folder 1/23)
    County-by-county vote tallies from the Oregon Secretary of State's office with regard to these two ballot measures, including polling information. Measure 8 (1988) revoked Governor Neil Goldschmidt's 1987 Executive Order banning sexual orientation discrimination in the state civil service, but the measure was found unconstitutional in 1992 by the Oregon Court of Appeals.
  - Text of Measure 9 & Background on OCA, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Blank Forms - Measure Argument & Petition for Measure Argument, 1993 (Box-folder 1/25)
    Forms that could be completed by any citizen and have his or her argument publiches in the Voter's Guide published by the Oregon Secretary of State.
  - Freedom Journal, OCA PAC, undated (Box-folder 1/26)
    A copy of a publication of the Oregon Citizens Alliance, including articles such as "Gay rights degrades Black Americans, other minorities"; "Homosexuality is not a minority"; and "Homosexuals are a rich class demanding special rights at the expense of true minorities."
  - Because..., undated (Box-folder 1/27)
    Statement of membership in lesbian and gay civil rights movement.
  - The Oregon Witness, July 1992 (Box-folder 1/28)
    Publication investigates the Oregon Citizens Alliance and the Christian Right.
  - Bill Clinton's Speech on Gay Rights, 1992 (Box-folder 1/29)
    Text of a speech given by presidential candidate, Bill Clinton.
  - Material on Investigation of the OCA, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/30)
    Miscellaneous information about the OCA, including a report from a private investigator.
  - Miscellaneous Handwritten Notes, Generally Dealing with Strategy, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Correspondence, Notes, and Other Material Dealing with Budget and Fiscal Matters, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/32)
  - Strategy Information: No On 9, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/33)
    Includes field plans, rally information, speaker's bureau and mailing list exchange information.
  - Promotional Brochures from Consultants on No On 9, circa 1993 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Post-Election Material, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/2)
    Correspondence, meeting minutes, and notes on aftermath of defeat of Measure 9 and plans for continued organization.
  - Secretary of State Election Reports, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/3)
    Contains financial reports and correspondence between Secretary of State's office and No On 9 Committee
  - All Vendor Expenses, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/4)
    Alphabetical list of all vendors paid during No On 9 campaign and the amount paid.
  - In-Kind Contributions, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/5)
    Miscellaneous in-kind contributions from individuals and businesses.
  - Sample Checks from No On 9, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/6)
    Blank checks showing address and telephone number of organization.
  - Dance For Diversity, undated (Box-folder 2/7)
    Ticket stubs from fundraising dance; includes ticket-buyers names & addresses.
  - Miscellaneous Volunteer Information, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
    Offers of donations, collection of signatures, and phone banks.
  - Ticket Captains, undated (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Button & Bumper Sticker Sales Logs, circa 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Button & Bumper Sticker Sales Logs - Janice, circa 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Button & Bumper Sticker Sales Logs - Anne, circa 1992-1993 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Report of Cash Receipts and Expenses By Month: August 23, 1992 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Business Breakfast Checks and Pledges, undated (Box-folder 3/3)
    Includes pledge sheets with notations. Legacy Health System pledge notation (on reverse) indicates this was the first time the corporation took a position on an Oregon ballot measure.
  - Nirvana T-Shirt Sales, 1992 (Box-folder 3/4)
    Logs of tee shirt sales at a No On 9 benefit concert by the rock band, Nirvana.
  - Dine Against 9 Flyer, undated (Box-folder 3/5)
    Flyer for restaurant fundraiser to support No On 9.
  - Letters to Federal and State Elections Agencies, 1992 (Box-folder 3/6)
    Letters deal with No On 9 committee's failure to file timely financial reports.
  - Auction Items, 4/2/93, 1993 (Box-folder 3/7)
    Roster of items donated by individuals or businesses to auction in support of No On 9.
  - Auction Items, 9/16/92, 1992 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Alphabetical Listing of Hate Free Oregon Database, 1992 (Box-folder 3/9)
    Roster of businesses, presumably those who donated to No On 9 campaign.
  - Contributions by City and State, undated (Box-folder 3/10)
    Records of contributions in dollars and numbers of contributors by cities and by states.
  - Alpha List of No On 9 Button Sales, 1992 (Box-folder 3/11)
    Record of persons buying No On 9 buttons. Contains name, address, amount donated, and, usually, occupation. 196 pages.
  - Right to Privacy PAC, 1992 (Box-folder 3/12)
    List of contributions to No On 9 by the Right to Privacy PAC.
  - SEL reporting forms for the Oregon Secretary of State
    - SEL 233 Form (In-Kind), 1992 (Box-folder 3/13)
      "Part III: In-Kind, Accounts Receivable and Accounts Payable" printout (1st pre-election), 160 pages, incomplete.
    - SEL 232 Form (Expenditures & Loans), 1992 (Box-folder 3/14)
      "Part II: Campaign Expenditures And Loan Payments" printout (1st pre-election), 126 pages, incomplete.
    - SEL 232 Form (Expenditures & Loans), 1992 (Box-folder 3/15)
      "Part II: Campaign Expenditures And Loan Payments" printout (2nd pre-election), 49 pages.
    - SEL 233 Form (In-Kind), 1992 (Box-folder 3/16)
      "Part III: In-Kind, Accounts Receivable and Accounts Payable" printout (annual supplemental), 1 page.
    - SEL 232 Form (Expenditures & Loans), 1993 (Box-folder 3/17)
      "Part II: Campaign Expenditures And Loan Payments" printout (Other), 1 page.
    - SEL 232 Form (Expenditures & Loans), 1993 (Box-folder 3/18)
      "Part II: Campaign Expenditures And Loan Payments" printout (annual supplemental), 31 pages.
    - SEL 232 Form (Expenditures & Loans), 1992 (Box-folder 3/19)
      "Part II: Campaign Expenditures And Loan Payments" printout (General post-election), 61 pages, incomplete.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans), 1993 (Box-folder 4/1)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (annual supplemental), 15 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans), 1992 (Box-folder 4/2)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (General, 2nd pre-election), 44 pages with cover letter.
    - List of Donor's Occupations and Employment, 1992 (Box-folder 4/4)
      Alphabetic Listing of donors to No On 9 with addresses and occupations. 136 pages. Dated November 24, 1992.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans), 1992 (Box-folder 4/3)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, post-election), 151 pages.
    - SEL 229 Form (Supplement re: Contributors), 1992 (Box-folder 4/5)
      "Supplement to Second Pre/Post Election Statement of Contributions" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), 3 separate reports.
    - SEL 233 Form (In-Kind), 1992 (Box-folder 4/6)
      "Part III: In-Kind, Accounts Receivable and Accounts Payable" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), 2 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) A-B, 1992 (Box-folder 4/7)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), section A-B, total report 638 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) C-E, 1992 (Box-folder 4/8)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), section C-E, total report 638 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) F-G, 1992 (Box-folder 4/9)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), section F-G, total report 638 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) H-J, 1992 (Box-folder 4/10)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), section H-J, total report 638 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) K-L, 1992 (Box-folder 4/11)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), section K-L, total report 638 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) M-O, 1992 (Box-folder 4/12)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), section M-O, total report 638 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) P-R, 1992 (Box-folder 4/13)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), section P-R, total report 638 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) S, 1992 (Box-folder 4/14)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), section S, total report 638 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) T-Z, 1992 (Box-folder 5/1)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 2nd pre-election), section T-Z, total report 638 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) A-B, 1992 (Box-folder 5/2)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 1st pre-election), section A-B, total report 791 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) C-E, 1992 (Box-folder 5/3)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 1st pre-election), section C-E, total report 791 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) F-G, 1992 (Box-folder 5/4)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 1st pre-election), section F-G, total report 791 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) H-K, 1992 (Box-folder 5/5)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 1st pre-election), section H-K, total report 791 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) L-M, 1992 (Box-folder 5/6)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 1st pre-election), section L-M, total report 791 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) N-Q, 1992 (Box-folder 5/7)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 1st pre-election), section N-Q, total report 791 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) R-S, 1992 (Box-folder 5/8)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 1st pre-election), section R-S, total report 791 pages.
    - SEL 231 Form (Contributions & Loans) T-Z, 1992 (Box-folder 5/9)
      "Part I: Contributions and Loans Received" printout (general, 1st pre-election), section T-Z, total report 791 pages.
  - Miscellaneous expenditures (not organized)
    Receipts and invoices for goods & services billed to No On 9 campaign. Materials are not organized.
    - 1992-1993 (Box-folder 6/1-6/5)
    - 1992-1993 (Box-folder 7/1-7/6)
  - Freedom Walk (fundraising event)
    - 1992 Oregon Freedom Walk - Forms (Box-folder 8/1)
      Advertising brochure, sample registration form for walkers, and volunteer information form used in conjunction with a No On 9 fundraising walk.
    - Pledge Sheets - Freedom Walk, 1992 (Box-folder 8/2-8/8)
      Pledge sheets turned in by those participating in walk. Materials not organized.
    - "Problems" Pledge Sheets, 1992 (Box-folder 8/9)
      Handwritten notes to follow up on specific pledge sheet data.
- Other related materials, Series B
  - deParrie v. City of Portland et al., 1992-1993 (Box-folder 5/10)
    Background material, including correspondence and discovery, of case of anti-gay plaintiff challenging (unsuccessfully) Portland's city ordinance outlawing sexual orientation discrimination.
  - Oregon State Bar Complaint - Les Krambeal v. Bernard Moore, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 5/11)
    Complaint and investigation by the Oregon State Bar that Moore threatened to reveal Krambeal's homosexuality during a civil trial in Medford, brought by Krambeal in a property dispute.
  - Miscellaneous Materials on Hate Crimes Based on Sexual Orientation, undated (Box-folder 5/12)
    Information about gathering statistics re: sexual orientation-related violence.
  - The Concord Principles, 1992 (Box-folder 5/13)
    Political agenda of Ralph Nader.